let's move now to swapping
we have this hierarchy of memories
we have large ones that are slow and small
ones
that are faster and we move information
between different
levels as we discussed before
now it might happen that the size of all logical
addresses
for all the processes we try to run are actually
larger than
the real physical memory we have
you can have a lot of programs that are stored
on disk and if
you were to execute all of them at the same
time and maybe
many instances of them at the same time you
might end up
having less actual physical memory than the
one you need
so swapping here refers to the task of taking
a process or
parts of a process
this will become clearer in the next lecture
from the main
memory and store them back to disk and then
from disk put
them back in memory when they're needed
this is what swapping refers to
so we say that we swap out a process or parts
of a process when
we move them from the main memory to the disk
and we swap
in them when we take them from the disk back
to the memory
now the concept is pretty simple
at least at this stage we will see that it
will get a bit
more complicated when we discuss virtual
memory in the
next lecture
but even at this point you can start thinking
about questions
like which processes can we swap?
how much time does it take?
when does it make sense to use swapping?
and so on?
if you remember what we discussed some lectures
ago when
we had this image here showing the process
control block
of different processes and we said the operating
system keeps
them in different queues
now if you have to swap out a process and
you have to pick
basically one of the process control blocks
you have in one
of these queue you can see that depending
on the queue that
is keeping the process control block it might
be easier
or not so easy to swap out the process
if they are in the ready queue for example they
are not running
they're not waiting for anything
so it's the ideal case
you can just put them back to disk if you
need space and
that's basically it
but on the other end if they are waiting for
something and
you put them to disk then you have to do this
carefully
meaning that if you are going to write let's
say there is
a process that is waiting for information
from the disk
when you get this information (you = the operating
system) you
need to write it somewhere
so if you decide to write it directly in the
memory of the
process then you cannot really swap the process
out or
at least you need to pay attention
because if you swap it out and you put another
process there
then you cannot write in that process the
data you got from
the disk
this of course would violate basic principle
of security
and correctness
and so on
you can of course keep track of what you get
from the disk
in portions of the main memory that belong
to the operating
system so even if you swap out a process that
is waiting
there is no risk of writing the information
it is waiting into
the memory of another process because this
stuff gets written
in parts of the memory that
belong to the operating
system
but then you need to write a more complicated
operating system
that has a dedicated portion of memory that
is used for these
kind of things and keeps track of what data
belongs to which
process and so on and so forth
so you see that things start getting complicated
if you look
up the different processes what they're doing
in the state
they are in
and so on of course you also have to think about
the time
it takes
and you can imagine that it's a slow operation
because it involves
the disk
if you have a process that is 100 megabytes
you can transfer
data 50 megabytes per second which is low
of course
now for a modern SSD disk
but you can imagine that maybe you have some
disk that you
need to reach through the network
so if you're something like this which is
sort of reasonable
not fantastic but
still reasonable
you see that it takes two seconds to swap
out a process
and if you have to swap the process back then
it's another
two seconds 4 seconds
it's basically an eternity from the perspective
of the
CPU and the speed at which the processes are
being context
switched by the operating system
and of course these are optimistic measures
because you
don't really know if during these four seconds
you have to
do other things
the operating system has to context switch
other processes
other processes require access to input output
maybe other processes have higher priorities
which means
that their requests will be prioritized and so
on
so these four seconds which is already a lot
it's the best
case in practice it can even be worst than this
so as we will see you want to minimize the
time it takes
to swap out processes
and actually we don't really swap out entire
processes
we do only swapping off part of them
but this way we discuss with virtual memory
and of course there are rules about when you
swap out and
in so if you take Unix and all operating
system modern
operating systems you see that basically it's
only when
you pass certain thresholds that you will
activate and deactivate
swapping you don't this if it's not really needed
and as I mentioned already too many times
so at this point we will see how this is actually
done with
virtual memory we will see there are many
smart ways to deal with the swapping